CHAPTER 3

Empowering Crime Victims:
Navigating Nepali Legal
Framework

SHOVA PATHAK

INTRODUCTION

The traditional criminal justice system pays very little attention to the victims of crime. For Salmond the purpose of criminal justice is punishment. We can regard it as a method of protecting society by reducing the occurrence of criminal behaviour or else we can consider it as an end. Punishment can protect society deterring potential offender and by reforming and turning him into a law-abiding citizen.1

Not only criminal justice system of states but also the international law paid sufficient attention to crime victims. Carlos Fernandez de Casadevante Romani wrote, ‘As it is well known and owing to the predominantly interstate structure of the international community, international norms are created to respond to states’ interests and goal. In this context attention to persons or individuals by states has only taken place in some field of international law.’2 According to him in case with human rights, international criminal law or international humanitarian law, the way in which the victims are considered differs.3

In human rights law, victims are acknowledged when the state is the author of the breach of an international obligation, but this branch of international law does not consider the breach of international obligations by non-state actors.4 In international criminal law and international humanitarian law on the other hand individuals may be regarded as victims as a consequence of acts perpetrated by individuals as well as by non-state actors.5 Therefore, international community has not yet codified binding international norms generally applicable to the victims of all types of crimes.

The victims have certain rights which must be protected to ensure that they get a fair treatment from the state agencies in the criminal justice process. Their concerns and needs must be responded sensitively by informing them about the progress of the case and by minimizing their miseries, offering protection and security to them and their families against any intimidation and retaliation. The police require the cooperation and support from the victim to prepare the case for prosecution in addition to tracing and apprehending the offender. Therefore, the protection of the crime victim is not only the protection offered to them but the protection of criminal justice and the whole justice system.

MEANING AND DEFINITION OF
CRIME VICTIM

‘Crime victim’ is a person who has been physically, financially or emotionally injured and/or had their property taken or damaged by someone committing a crime. Traditionally, the term crime victim has been defined as an individual who has been directly subjected to criminal activity.6 This definition of crime victim excludes the family members or defendant of the person who died because of crime. German criminologist Hans Joachim Schneider states that a victim can be an individual, an organization, ‘the moral order’ or the legal system of a state which is threatened, harmed, or destroyed by an action.7 The Declaration of Basic Principles of Justice for Victims of Crime and Abuse of Power defines crime victim in the following words:

‘Victims’ means persons who, individually or collectively, have suffered harm, including physical or mental injury, emotional suffering, economic loss or substantial impairment of their fundamental rights, through acts or omissions that are in violation of criminal laws operative within Member States, including those laws proscribing criminal abuse of power.8

Crime Victim Protection Act, 2075 (2018) has provided three types of victims namely First Degree Victim, Second Degree Victim and Family Victim in the form of a natural person. First Degree Victim means a person who as a result of the offender’s age, mental illness, diplomatic immunity or professional immunity does not have to bear criminal liability or the offender’s identity is unknown or charge is not made against the offender or the case related to the crime is taken back or the punishment imposed to the offender is pardoned or conviction is not made or regardless of the relation between the victim and offender, death occurred as a direct result of the crime commit detains the victim or loss is suffered and the term shall also indicate the person who dies or suffers loss while not engaging in crime in any of the following conditions:

1. While acting to stop the person from committing the crime.

2. While acting to provide reasonable support and rescue, in conditions when crime is being committed against a person, with an objective to prevent such a person from crime.

3. While attempting to arrest a person who is committing or has committed a crime or while providing help to an authorized person in course of arresting a suspicious, accused or convicted person.

Likewise, ‘Second Degree Victim’ means a person who is not involved in the crime committed or being committed against the First Degree Victim but as a result of being an eyewitness incurred loss and this term shall also mean a person not involved in the crime but has information of the crime or a guardian of a First Degree Minor Victim who incurred loss as a result of being an eyewitness and the term shall also mean the following persons who incurred loss as a result of having knowledge of the crime committed against the First Degree Victim:

(i) Guardian of First Degree Victim,

(ii) in case the First Degree Victim is a minor, and

(iii) in case the person incurring such loss is not involved in such crime.

‘Family Victim’ means the mother, father, husband, wife in consanguinity with the dead victim or any other person in the consanguinity family dependent on the victim who is not involved in the crime committed against the First Degree Victim as a direct consequence of which he or she died.

VICTIM OF CRIME UNDER CRIMINAL
JUSTICE SYSTEM

A justice system depends upon evidence against the case; they are appropriately being collected and presented before the courts. And, particularly, if fear prevails, collection of evidence is very difficult or not at all. The absence of evidence may finally lead to not taking up the cases or dismiss the charges against the accused, as the court can only consider on the matters brought before the court. This will lead to the space to weaken the case or escape the real culprits/perpetrators or lose the case.

Silencing victims through fear is one of the worst forms of impunity. It maintains the illusion of the rule of law and a legal system capable of following up wrongdoing. If any, complaints are made and if they are, they rarely result in prosecutions or convictions. Silence denies the existence of the problem; the problem may be known but is never spoken about.9 One of the challenges for many countries is in obtaining the cooperation of victims and witnesses to obtain important information and evidence about the criminal matters.10

The Declaration of Basic Principles of Justice for Victims of Crime and Abuse of Power, 1985, recognizes four basic rights of crime victims as:

• The right of access to trial proceedings and fair treatment.

• The right to compensation by the perpetrator.

• The right to compensation by the state.

• The right to necessary material, medical, psychological and social assistance from volunteer and public institutions.

The Constitution of Nepal drafted by the Constituent Assembly has guaranteed the right of crime victim including right to justice and compensation, for the first time in the world. The statutes drafted thereafter including the Muluki Criminal Code, 2017 and Muluki Criminal Procedure Code, 2017 and the Sentencing Act, 2017 have incorporated important provisions regrading the right of crime victims. Recently, the parliament has enacted comprehensive law for the protection of crime victim in 2018. In the later sections, the provisions of national law regarding crime victims including constitutional provisions, the provisions of general laws and specific legal provisions on rights to crime victim will be discussed in detail.

CONCEPT OF RIGHTS OF VICTIMS
OF CRIME

The word ‘right’ generally means a claim or an interest provided by the law or rights recognized and protected by law. The rights of crime victims mean the rights or claim of the victim of crime in the criminal justice process when they are a direct or an indirect victim. According to the US Code SS 3771(1) there are the following rights:

1. The right to be reasonably protected from the accused.

2. The right to reasonable, accurate and timely notice of any public court proceeding, or any parole proceeding, involving the crime or of any release or escape of the accused.

3. The right not to be excluded from any such public court proceeding, unless the court, after receiving clear and convincing evidence, determines that testimony by the victim would be materially altered if the victim hears other testimony at that proceeding.

4. The right to be reasonably heard at any public proceeding in the district court involving release, plea, sentencing or any parole proceeding.

5. The reasonable right to confer with the attorney for the Government in the case.

6. The right to full and timely restitution as provided in law.

7. The right to proceedings free from unreasonable delay.

8. The right to be treated with fairness and with respect for the victim’s dignity and privacy.

9. The right to be informed in a timely manner of any plea bargain or deferred prosecution agreement.

10. The right to be informed of the rights under this section and the services described in section 503(c) of the Victims’ Rights and Restitution Act of 1990 [42 U.S.C. 10607(c)]/[1] and provided contact information for the Office of the Victims’ Rights Ombudsman of the Department of Justice.11

According to the Declaration of Basic Principles of Justice for Victims of Crime and Abuse of Power, 1985,

• The right of access to trial proceedings and fair treatment.

• The right to compensation by the perpetrator.

• The right to compensation by the state.

• The right to necessary material, medical, psychological and social assistance from volunteer and public institutions

THE RIGHT TO ACCESS TO JUSTICE
AND FAIR TREATMENT

The crime victim thus receives the right to respect and acknowledgements at all levels of the criminal proceedings that is they have right to access the mechanism of justice and to prompt redress for the harm they have suffered. They have the right to receive continual information about how the case is proceeding, the right to give information to those responsible for decisions regarding the criminal, access to legal counsel, protection of personal integrity and physical security and the right to economic compensation.

RIGHT TO RESTITUTION

Restitution means payment made to the victim for damage suffered because of crime. It is intended to repay victims for their losses caused by the crime. The Declaration on the Rights of Victim emphasized on the fair restitution to the victim of crime. According to the paragraph 8, offenders or third parties responsible for their behaviour should, where appropriate, make fair restitution to victims, their families or dependents. Such restitution should include the return of property or payment for the harm or loss suffered, reimbursement of expenses incurred because of the victimization, the provision of services and the restoration of rights.

RIGHT TO COMPENSATION

It is the duty of the state to protect the life and property of people. The consequence of the state’s failure should not be borne by the people. This matter has been recognized by the declaration. The declaration provides that when compensation is not fully available from the offender or other sources, States should endeavour to provide financial compensation to the victims who have sustained significant bodily injury or impairment of physical or mental health as a result of serious crimes; the family, in particular dependents of persons who have died or become physically or mentally incapacitated as a result of such victimization.

RIGHT TO ASSISTANCE

Crime victims require assistance in various aspects including medical, psychological and social assistance for their physical protection as well as for successful prosecution against the wrongdoer. According to paragraphs 14 to 17 of the declaration, the victims should receive the necessary material, medical, psychological and social assistance through governmental, voluntary, community-based and indigenous means. They should be informed of the availability of health and social services and other relevant assistance and be readily afforded access to them. Police, justice, health, social service and other personnel concerned should receive training to sensitize them to the needs of victims and guidelines to ensure proper and prompt aid. In providing services and assistance to victims, attention should be given to those who have special needs.

RIGHTS OF CRIME VICTIMS UNDER
NEPALI LEGAL FRAMEWORK

CONSTITUTIONAL PROVISION ON THE
RIGHTS OF CRIME VICTIMS

Nepali criminal justice system has taken a big leap in the protection of the rights of crime victim in recent years Constitution of Nepal made by the Constituent Assembly has guaranteed the right of the crime victim for the first time. Article 21 of the Constitutions under the Right of Victim of crime provides:12

Right of Victim of Crime: (1) A victim of crime shall have the right to get information about the investigation and proceedings of a case in which he or she is the victim.

(2) A victim of crime shall have the right to justice including social rehabilitation and compensation in accordance with law.

The Constitution of Nepal for the first time in the world has engraved the rights of the Crime Victim. The victim of crime not only has the right to get information regarding the investigation and proceeding of the case but also the right to justice including social rehabilitation and compensation in accordance with law. This constitutional provision has a wider connotation. According to this Constitutional provision the crime victim has the right to get information about the proceeding of the case at every step of criminal process from investigation to prosecution, trial, appeal and execution of the judgement. The investigating and prosecuting authorities as well as the court have the duty to inform the victim of the proceeding of the case. The crime victim also has the right to justice including social rehabilitation and compensation.

PROVISION OF GENERAL LAW REGARDING
THE RIGHTS OF CRIME VICTIMS

There have been very few legal provisions regarding to the rights of crime victims before the commencement of this Act. These provisions have limited connotation and are limited only to some aspects of victim’s right like protection of the victim, privacy and compensation. These provisions do not cover the most important aspect of right that is the right to access to justice. However, the statutes drafted after the commencement of the constitution, i.e. the Muluki Criminal Code, 2017 and Muluki Criminal Procedure Code, 2017 and the Sentencing Act, 2017 have incorporated important provisions regarding the right of crime victims.

The Human Trafficking and Transportation (Control) Act, 2007 has made some provision about the rights of crime victims including the protection of the confidentiality of the crime victim and right to compensation. ‘Caste Based Discrimination and Untouchability (Offence and Punishment) Act, 2068 (2011)’ has criminalized the act of discrimination and made provision for restitution to the victim. Likewise, the Children Act, 2018 has ensured various rights of child victims including the right to information the language he or she understands, to participate, right confidentiality, right to compensation from the offender as well as from State, right to free legal aid and socio-psychological counselling service, right to free service of the translator, sign language expert or interpreter, right to get free of cost, the copy of the documents including the decisions and orders, right to get police protection for safety against the probable.13 Domestic Violence (Crime and Punishment) Act, 2066 (2009) offered for immediate protection of the victim and protecting her from further victimization,14 provision of in camera proceedings and hearings of the complaint.15 Motor Vehicles and Transport Management Act, 1993 has the provision of compensation and medical expense to be paid to the victim by the offender in case of loss of life, injury to body or loss of property.16

The codes relating to criminal justice including the Muluki Criminal Code, 2017, Muluki Criminal Procedure Code, 2017 and Sentencing Act, 2017 and rules thereof have been brought into commencement of the Constitution of Nepal in 2015. Section 32 of the Country Criminal Code guarantees the same right in the similar term under the title ‘Victim of crime to be entitled to obtain information of proceedings of case and compensation’. Section 13(c) of the Criminal Offence (Determination and Execution of Sentence) Act, 2017 has provided that the court, while determining the sentence has to take into account of delivering justice along with compensation to the victim.17

RIGHTS OF THE CRIME VICTIM UNDER CRIME
VICTIM PROTECTION ACT, 2018

Constitutional guarantee of the rights of crime victims and formulation of Crime Victim Protection Act, 2075 has been significant achievement in the field of rights of crime victims. The Act has classified victim as ‘Victim of First Grade’, ‘Victim of Second Grade’ and ‘Family Victim’ and made provision for providing compensation and relief. The rights guaranteed by the Act can be discussed under the following headings:

Right to Protection and Security

It is the foremost right of the victim to be protected from further victimization her/him and his/her family from the offender. Protection includes protection from attack, loss, fear, threat or intimidation that may be against the victim or the close relative of the victim and the person dependent on the victim from the suspected person, accused, convict or person related to the convict or the witness of accused.18

Right to Fair Treatment and Non-discrimination

Victim shall have the right to receive civilized, noble, fair and dignified treatment in criminal justice process.19 Victim shall not be discriminated in the criminal justice process on the basis of his or her religion, race, sex, caste, ethnicity, gender, origin, language, marital status, family status, age, physical or mental illness, disability or ideology or such other basis.20 However, the victims with the special needs like minor, elderly citizens or physically or mentally incapable persons have to be considered in the context of criminal justice process.

Right to Privacy

The Act has also guaranteed the victim of some sensitive crimes like rape, incest, human trafficking, sexual harassment, the right to privacy in the course of investigation, inquiry, prosecution and judicial proceedings.21 If any deed and testimony or deputation has to be made in the course of investigation, inquiry and judicial proceedings of the crimes it has to be prepared by presenting victim in a way to not reveal his or her identity. It has to be made by changing the real voice of the victim. If video conference has to be made in a way the offender is unable to see or hear.

Right to Information Relating to Investigation

The investigation officer, prosecutors and the court have to provide information regarding the investigation, prosecution and court proceeding in the case. It enables the victim to know the progress of the case as well as take further step in protecting her interest and securing justice.

Right to Express Opinion22

The victim’s right to express opinion about the process of making decision relating to prosecution, plea bargaining, mitigating the sentence, making additional charges, making pre-sentencing report, determining sentence and making decision regarding diversion, probation, parole, suspended sentence, open prison, community service or any other facilities of similar nature to the offender.23

Right to Participation

Another important right of the victim is the right to be present and make one’s statement in the proceedings relating to the court hearing in relation to the crime.24 The victim has the right to express opinion in the sentencing process also.

Right to Make Written Application or Appeal

The victim has the right to make a written application before the concerned agency or authority requesting for filing an application or appeal against the order of the court if Government of Nepal has the right to file an application or appeal against such order or decision of the court according to prevailing law.25

Right to Compensation

Right to receive compensation is another important right of the crime victim for realization of justice. Section 18 provides that if the victim is entitled to get compensation according to this Act or other prevailing law and if he/she requests for information about it the prosecuting authority should give information to the victim in relation to the procedures to be fulfilled relating to receiving compensation.26 Section 19 of the Act provides that the victim shall have the right to receive compensation for the loss he/she suffered.27

Right to Stay in a Separate Chamber During the Hearing

In the course of the hearing of the offence, the court may provide a separate chamber for the victim so that he or she can stay separately from the accused, person related to the accused and witness of the accused.28 If it is not possible to provide separate chamber make necessary arrangement for the safety and interest of the victim so that the accused, person related to the accused and witness of the accused cannot contact the victim, except as otherwise ordered by the court.

Right to Have Property Returned

The victim has the right to have his or her property taken under control during investigation or for evidence, returned immediately after the completion of investigation. However, if such property is to be submitted to the court for evidence or there is a dispute as to the ownership or possession of the property, the property shall not be returned before the dispute is settled. The court may, if it so thinks necessary, make an order to return such property before the dispute is settled.29

Right to Social Rehabilitation

Rehabilitation is a crucial right of the crime victim to enable him/ her live a normal life. The victim should be protected from further victimization and revictimization. It depends on the context, such measures range from external oversight and monitoring mechanisms to the establishment of judicial remedies, the strengthening of the judiciary’s independence. The Act has a provision regarding social rehabilitation of the victim however, it has not defined what social means.

Interim Compensation

According to the Section 29 of the Act in case victim has to be immediately treated or if compensation or any form of relief amount has to be provided, the court may give order to conduct medical treatment or to provide interim form of compensation or relief for such person. Such compensation shall be provided from the Fund.

Right to Appoint Legal Practitioner

Right to access to justice includes the right to effective representation which is not possible without legal practitioner. Although, the prosecutor represents the victim in the court, the victim also has the right to representation with the help of a law practitioner. The Act ensures that crime victims have the right to appoint a separate legal practitioner in the criminal justice process if they wish.30

ROLE OF SUPREME COURT IN THE PROTECTION
OF RIGHTS OF CRIME VICTIMS

The Supreme Court of Nepal has played an important role in the protection of the rights of victims of crime. It has taken a proactive approach in ensuring access to justice, safeguarding victims, and securing compensation and restitution for them. The Court’s decisions and orders reflect its commitment to these vital protections.

VICTIM’S RIGHT TO ACCESS TO JUSTICE

The Supreme Court of Nepal has issued a landmark ruling in the case crime victim Suntali Dhami31 reinforcing the protection of the right to access justice. The Court held that the malafide and arbitrary exercise of prosecutorial power is subject to judicial review. Likewise, Supreme Court in writ of mandamus of Punyashila Dawadi Ghimire vs. PMO32 and others held that:

The state, for purpose of making the access to justice easy has to adopt proper measures. The environment of realizing the care and protection of state by the victim has to be created. The state has to take measures to stop the barriers that discourage the women victim of rape and human trafficking from seeking judicial remedies and have been forced to live with mental, physical and psychological suffering.

The Supreme Court has made similar order in the writ of Certiorari and Mandamus of Jyoti Lamsal vs. GoN, PM and PMO33 and in the writ of certiorari of Narayan Singh Rajpoot vs. Office of the Attorney General of Nepal.34 In Narayan Singh Rajpoot case the Supreme Court held:

There is the provision of police for carrying out investigation of crime and the government has also made the provision of Government Attorney to screen the evidence, prosecute and defend the case in the court on behalf of the victim.

The Supreme Court, then the writ of Mandamus of Meera Dhungana vs. PMO35 issued a six-point directive to the respondents, instructing them to establish a plan to provide the victim with information about the investigation from the concerned police office. The directives also required the prosecutor to inform about the charges and court’s judgement, including copies of the charge sheet and judgement.

CONFIDENTIALITY OF THE VICTIM

Protection of the confidentiality of victim is directly connected with her physical protection. Supreme Court of Nepal has played very important role in the protection of confidentiality of victim. The Supreme Court, in a writ petition for Mandamus filed by Sapana Pradhan Malla, issued a directive order to the Government of Nepal, the Council of Ministers and the Ministry of Law and Justice to formulate laws for maintaining confidentiality in special types of cases involving women, children or individuals infected from HIV Aids, outlining the rights and responsibility of the concerned parties. The Court also issued directives consisting of 13 Sections to remain effective until such a law is formulated. In the order, the Supreme Court held that,36 in the human trafficking case of Sunil Lama vs. GoN, it analysed the principle of victimology for the first time and concluded that:

. . . the defendant alluring the victim of marrying her took to brothel of India and sold her. The victim got out of the life of hell of the brothel, lodged FIR and her statement has been certified from the court . . . the statement of the victim certified from the court is admissible as evidence even if she has not testified in the court.37

SUPREME COURT APPROACH REGARDING COMPENSATION

Compensation is essential for protecting and assisting victims of crime. The Supreme Court before the commencement of Crime Victim Protection Act, 2018 developed a procedure for compensating rape victims due to the absence of clear recovery procedure. In GoN vs. Swosti Baral, the Court held that it is the government’s duty to claim compensation for the victim by ascertaining the defendant’s property details and specifying the grounds and reasons for recovering the compensation in the charge sheet.38 The Supreme Court in the rape case of Rakesh Kumar Singh vs. GoN39 held that in rape cases the District Court has to give information to the victim after final judgement and execute the judgement as well as recover the compensation to the victim. This although, is not written in the law. The most significant and inspiring judgement regarding compensation to the victim is the ruling of the Court in Lok Bahadur Sharki et al. vs. GoN.40 The Supreme Court held that:

From now onwards, it is appropriate to provide compensation fixed by the final judgement of the court immediately to the victim of the crimes of such nature in which compensation is payable, by establishing a separate fund by the government and recover it from the offender as government due. Therefore, it is required to make necessary infrastructure by the government in this regard.

CONCLUSION

The new Constitution of Nepal has brought a paradigm shift in the role and status of victims in the criminal justice system. The Crime Victim Protection Act, 2018, has been enacted and implemented for translating these rights into practice. The Act has been implemented and the rights of crime victims have been safeguarded. A Victim Relief Fund has been established and a relief fee is levied from every convict in a criminal case. However, the situation of crime victim cannot change overnight, as it is not easy to implement new concepts in practice. The rights enshrined in the Constitution or laws must be put into practice through the collaborative efforts of all relevant stakeholders, which is a very challenging task. The government must manage this effectively. A clear understanding of the concept related to victims’ right and protection measures is essential for safeguarding victims’ right in every stage of the criminal justice procedure. To internationalize the concept of victim justice among key stakeholders, sensitization programmes should be carried out. Fundamentals of victim protection must be included in training course designed for judicial cadres, prosecutors, police investigators and defence lawyers. Additionally, a crime victim information mechanism should be established within police stations and public prosecutor offices to provide regular updates on the progress of their cases. Various legislations contain the provisions related to victim protection and compensation. Harmonization of these legal provisions is essential to ensure consistency in practice.

NOTES

1. P. J. Fitzerald, Salmond on Jurisprudence, 12th edn. (1966), N.M. Tripathee, Bombay, 94.

2. Carlos Farnandez de Casadevante Romani (2010), Max Plank UNYB14, p. 221.

3. Ibid.

4. Ibid.

5. Ibid.

6. Magnus Lindgren and Vesna Nikoliæ-Ristanoviæ (2011), Crime Victims: International and Serbian Perspective, Organization for Security and Constitution Cooperation in Europe, Mission to Serbia, Law Enforcement Department, 19.

7. Ibid.

8. Article 1(1) of The Declaration of Basic Principles of Justice for Victims of Crime and Abuse of Power, 1985.

9. V.G. Paulina and F. Carla (2009), ‘Ending Threats and Reprisals Against Victims of Torture and Related International Crimes: A Call to Action, 6.

10. Kramer, K., (2010), ‘Witness Protection as a Key Tool in Addressing Serious and Organized Crime’, 7-9 December in 4th the Regional Seminar on Good Governance for Southeast Asian Countries, Manila, Philippines, p. 3.

11. 18 U.S. Code § 3771—Crime victims’ rights, Retrieved 13 July 2022. https://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/text/18/3771.

12. The Constitution of Nepal, Article 21.

13. Children Act, 2018, Section 25.

14. Domestic Violence (Crime and Punishment) Act, 2066 (2009), Section 6.

15. Ibid., Section 7.

16. Motor Vehicle and Transportation Management Act, 1993 Sections 160, 161, 163.

17. Criminal Offence (Determination and Execution of Sentence) Act, 2017, Section 13(c).

18. Crime Victim Protection Act, 2019, Section 10.

19. Ibid., Section 4.

20. Ibid., Section 5.

21. Ibid., Section 6.

22. Ibid., Section 11.

23. Ibid.

24. Ibid., Section 13.

25. Ibid., Section 17.

26. Ibid., Section 18.

27. Ibid., Section 19.

28. Ibid., Section 14.

29. Ibid., Section 15.

30. Ibid., Section 12.

31. Suntali Dhami (Shah) vs. Office of the Prime Minister and Council of Ministers et al., NKP 2068, vol. 1, Decision No. 8541.

32. NKP 2074 vol. 1, Decision No. 9741.

33. NKP 2067 vol. 11, Decision No. 8507.

34. NKP 2070 vol. 1, Decision No. 8949.

35. NKP 2070 vol. 3, Decision No. 8973.

36. NKP 2064 vol. 9, Decision No. 7880.

37. Supreme Court, Subjectwise Collection of the Summary of Precedent, Criminal Law, Part 2, 2066, p. 1.

38. NKP 2062 vol. 11, Decision No. 7626.

39. NKP 2064 vol. 1, Decision No. 7810.

40. NKP 2072 No. 2, Decision No. 9346.

REFERENCES

Askari, H. (1988). Victimology. Lex Et Juris, International Current, 30 July.

Bastola, G.K. (2046 BS). Pidit Kshatipurak Shastra: Ek Charcha (A Discussion on Victimology). Jodhpur: Kanoon Prakashak, 11.

Cho, K.S. (2014). The Current Situation and Challenges of Measures for Victims of Crime in the Korean Criminal Justice System. In The 144th International Senior Seminar Visiting Experts’ Papers (Series 81, p. 77).

Co, M.G. The Enhancement of Appropriate Measures for Victim of Crime at Each Stage of the Philippine Criminal Justice. Retrieved from www.unafei.or.jp/english/pdf/RS_No81/No81_15PA_Co.pdf

Doak, J. (2015). Enriching Trial Justice for Crime Victims in Common Law Systems: Lessons from Transitional Environments. Retrieved from http://irep.ntu.ac.uk/id/eprint/27097/1/PubSub4489_Doak.pdf

Dussich, J.P.J. (2006). Victimology—Past, Present and Future. In 131st International Senior Seminar Visiting Experts’ Papers. Retrieved from https://www.unafei.or.jp/publications/pdf/RS_No70/No70_12VE_Dussich.pdf

European Union Agency for Fundamental Rights (2019). Justice for victims of violent crime: Part 1 – standards. Retrieved from https://fra.europa.eu/sites/default/files/fra_uploads/fra-2019-justice-for-victims-of-violent-crime-part-1-standards_en.pdf

Jaishankar, K. (2014). Implementing Victims’ Rights in Newly-Industrialized Countries: Reflections on Major Challenges and Recommendations for the Future. In Justice for Victims.

Kramer, K. (2010). Witness Protection as a Key Tool in Addressing Serious and Organized Crime.

Lindgren, M. and Nikoliæ-Ristanoviæ, V. (2011). Crime Victims: International and Serbian Perspective. Organization for Security and Cooperation in Europe, Mission to Serbia, Law Enforcement Department.

Nepal (2011). Caste-based Discrimination and Untouchability (Offence and Punishment) Act.

Nepal (2017). The Country (Muluki) Criminal Code.

Nepal (2017). The Country (Muluki) Criminal Procedure Code.

Nepal (2018). The Crime Victim Protection Act.

Nepal (2017). Criminal Offence (Sentencing and Execution) Act.

Nepal (2009). Domestic Violence (Offence and Punishment) Act.

Nepal (2007). Human Trafficking and Transportation Control Act.

Nepal (1993). Motor Vehicles and Transport Management Act.

Paulina, V.G. and Carla, F. (2009). Ending Threats and Reprisals Against Victims of Torture and Related International Crimes: A Call to Action. London: The REDRESS Trust.

Romani, C.F. de C. (2010). International Law of Victims. Max Planck.

Siddiqu, A.E. (1993). Criminology Problems and Perspectives.

Shrestha, S.K. (2001). A Step Towards Victim Justice System: Nepalese Perspectives (1st edn.).

——, (2017). Victimology (1st edn.). Pairavi Publication.

Tiwari, P. (2012). Victimology: A Sub-Discipline of Criminology. Dehradun Law Review, 4(1).

United Nations Office on Drugs and Crime (2009). Handbook for Professionals and Policymakers on Justice Matters Involving Child Victims and Witnesses of Crime. Criminal Justice Handbook Series, 1.

United Nations Economic and Social Council (2005). Basic principles on the use of restorative justice programmes in criminal matters. Retrieved from https://www.un.org/en/ecosoc/docs/2005/resolution%202005-20.pdf

United Nations Office on Drugs and Crime (2005). Bangkok declaration: Synergies and responses: Strategic alliances in crime prevention and criminal justice. Retrieved from https://www.unodc.org/pdf/crime/congress11/BangkokDeclaration.pdf

U.S. Code § 3771. Crime victims’ rights. Retrieved 13 July 2022, from https://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/text/18/3771

von Hentig, H. (1940). Remarks on the Interaction of Perpetrator and Victim. Journal of Criminal Law and Criminology.

Wemmers, J.A. (2009). Where do they belong? Giving Victims a Place in the Criminal Justice Process. Criminal Law Forum, 20, 395. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10609-009-9107-z.

CHAPTER 4

Foundations for Durability and
Stability in Democratic
Constitutions

REWATI RAJ TRIPATHI AND
PRABHAT CHHETRI

MARXIST APPROACH ON CONSTITUTION
AND LAW

Marx distinguished between the economic structure of society (the ‘base’ or ‘infrastructure’) and the ‘superstructure’ which rose upon this ‘real foundation’.1 The term ‘superstructure’ is used in three senses: (i) legal and political forms which express existing real relations of production; (ii) forms of consciousness which express a particular class view of the world; and (iii) a process in which individuals become aware of fundamental economic conflicts and fight those out.2

Examining the relationship between Capitalism and Marxism concerning law and constitutional interpretation reveals significant divergence in their perspectives. Marxist ideology interprets law through three fundamental principles: dialectical materialism, the law of production and historical materialism. In contrast, capitalists view the constitution and law as inherently self-sustaining entities, treating concepts like the rule of law, capitalist or bourgeois societal structures and the separation of powers as immutable truths.

Nevertheless, Marxists view law as a tool wielded by the ruling class to oppress the governed. In a class-based society, law serves as a weapon used by the dominant class to subjugate the subordinate class. It does not exist in isolation but functions as a superstructure built upon the economic and social foundations of society, shaped by economic forces. For Marx, while philosophers have interpreted the world, the ultimate duty lies over turning it for a better one. Thus, involving society and understanding law as dynamic are essential corner stones for a successful legal system.

According to Marxist theory, all ideological constructs, including religion, moral philosophy, art, as well as political and legal institutions, are not autonomous entities but rather grounded in the economic and political framework of society. These constructs do not derive from any inherent or eternal notions of law and justice. In Marxist thought, law and the state are inseparable; a state devoid of law is inconceivable. In the earliest stages of societal formation, such as in primitive communist societies, there was an absence of formal legal systems, a characteristic that is anticipated to persist in future communist societies. With the emergence of the concept of personal property, societal classes began to form, leading to the progression through various socioeconomic stages—including slave societies, feudal societies, capitalist societies and socialist societies—all culminating in the eventual establishment of a communist society. In this future communist society, economic contradictions are expected to be resolved, thereby ending the exploitation of individuals by others and rendering the law, as a tool of exploitation, unnecessary.

During the transitional phase from capitalism to socialism and ultimately to communism, following a proletarian-led revolution, the role of law persists as a mechanism for facilitating the transition. Throughout this transitional period, the law serves multiple functions, including the facilitation of the collective ownership of means of production, in doctrination of individuals in communist ideals and the suppression of reactionary movements seeking to revert to previous socioeconomic structures. Therefore, during this transition, the law is viewed as a two-edged tool that is employed to educate the public and quell counterrevolutionary elements. However, as society moves closer to communism, the need for laws as tools of oppression decreases, eventually causing them to become outdated and wither away.

The following three laws of materialist dialectic are: the law of unity and struggle of opposites, law of quantitative to qualitative change and law of negation of negation. The unity and struggle between opposites constitute the fundamental law of materialist dialectic. According to this principle, every object embodies two conflicting aspects, which engage in perpetual conflict, compelled to intermingle for their own sustenance. Both aspects are dynamic and vibrant, often transforming into each other under certain circumstances. For instance, capitalists and the proletariat represent mutually contradictory facets of society. While their interests diverge, they are intricately intertwined internally, forming a unity between opposing elements. The capitalists have to buy labour power for production and the workers have to sell labour power to satisfy their needs, indicating a unity between opposite forces. However, class struggle between them is still fierce as capitalists try to make as much profit as possible while workers want to ensure higher wages. This central conflict clearly shows that these two concepts are often at odds with each other.

When conflicting forces struggle for dominance, a victor may emerge, or a new element may develop, signifiying a change. These changes can be categorized into two types: quantitative and qualitative.

A gradual progression within an object without altering its form or quality constitutes a quantitative change. Conversely, a qualitative change involves a radical transformation in both form and quality, often occurring suddenly. For example, the gradual heating of water illustrates a quantitative change as the water retains its form and properties throughout the process. However, once the temperature reaches 100O Celsius, the water undergoes a qualitative change, boiling and transforming into steam and exhibiting distinct properties and form.

The third principle, the law of the negation of negation, refers to the replacement of one entity by another. While this process may seem to replicate the original entity, it ultimately leads to the emergence of a qualitatively distinct object. This principle applies to societal development as well. The emergence of class society negated primitive communist societies, while future communist societies will negate class societies. Similarly, the evolution from spontaneous materialism to mechanical materialism and subsequently to dialectical materialism, exemplifies the negation of negation. However, in the envisioned classless society of the future, where conflicting classes are absent, this process of negation will cease. It is believed that in such a society, where economic and social structures will be separated, exploitation and class differentiation will disappear, eliminating both rulers and the ruled, as well as exploiters and the exploited.

CONSTITUTION AS A POLITICO-LEGAL
DOCUMENT

Advocates of capitalist democracy regard the law as relatively autonomous but they consider the constitution as a politico-legal document. The constitution encompasses principles and practices that establish the fundamental framework of governance for an organized political community. It directs politics by defining the distribution and utilization of state power. The constitution is both a political and a legal document, as it ensures the freedoms and rights of citizens, legally regulates the government and can be enforced by the courts.

Marxists or socialists perceive the constitution crafted under their leadership as a revolutionary manifesto. Constitutions emerging after socialist revolutions aim to comprehensively overhaul established civil societies based on the principles and achievements of the original social revolution, reflecting the ideologies and impacts inherent in it. Such constitutions are designed to dismantle existing structures entirely and redefine their components. They delineate the rights, roles and responsibilities within the state system, excluding political participation from specific classes (counter-revolutionary classes). In such contexts, ultimate authority over the state resides in the hands of well-organized revolutionary leaders.3

In contrast, when a state system arises from compromise, the constitution is typically formulated through collaboration among stakeholders or a conference of stakeholders. State power is distributed among various entities through the participation of stakeholders under the principles of federalism. In class-based political systems, where two distinct classes coexist, one class views itself as the sole architect of the nation’s fate, assuming the privilege and responsibility of drafting the constitution, which is subsequently conferred by the higher authorities. The role of the other class primarily involves adhering to the provisions of the constitution, where consent is characterized by faith or allegiance to authority. Examples of top-down constitutions given by ruling classes include those proclaimed by monarchs during the medieval period and constitutions prior to the Second People’s Movement.

FOUNDATIONS OF DURABILITY AND STABILITY
OF THE CONSTITUTION

Advocates of capitalist democracy consider the constitution as a sacred document based on democratic constitutionalism and generally do not accept its rewriting. It is due to the circumstances surrounding the capitalist revolution, which recently liberated itself from British imperialism. Thomas Jefferson, one of the architects of the American Constitution, remarked to James Madison in discussion that the Constitution should be rewritten by every generation,4 emphasizing that the deceased should not dictate governance to the living. The US Constitution of 1789 stands as the oldest surviving constitution. Historian Steven Ming writes that the United States has the oldest written national framework of government in the world.5 By the end of the twentieth century, he writes, 159 countries had written constitutions and 101 of those had been in practice since 1970.6 However, America is the only nation that has been governed by the same constitution for two centuries.

On the other hand, in France, around the same time—namely, after the French Revolution in 1789—fifteen constitutions were enacted following the Constitution of the First Republic, issued in 1791. Consequently, among the contemporaneous constitutions, the American constitution has endured for approximately 230 years with only twenty-seven amendments. Through this constitution, the nation, recently liberated from imperialism, was able to evolve into the world’s most powerful country, despite enduring two civil wars and two world wars. On the other hand, France enacted 16 constitutions during the same period of upheaval and considering the average lifespan of these constitutions, it appears that a new constitution was drafted approximately every twenty years. More surprisingly, the French Additional Act of 1815 was enforced for only twenty-one days.

Before discussing the reasons for this, it is relevant to discuss the background of the constitution. The constitution lays down the basic principles governing the state’s operation. As a framework of government, the constitution describes the basic structure of the government, institutions and political process. Additionally, as a protector of rights, it declares certain rights as fundamental or basic rights and outlines measures for their protection within society. Constitutions designed post-revolution or after reform movements incorporate agendas raised during the revolution and the aim to address the people’s expectations during the implementation of the constitution. The success of a constitution is largely determined by its ability to meet the expectations placed upon it.

The durability of the Constitution is not an end in itself. Jefferson contends that the Constitution serves as a remedial measure. Professor Joshua Saylor of Sandra Day O’Connor College of Law argues that the framers of the American Constitution aimed to foster democratic discourse, safeguard against governmental fragmentation and abuse and equitably distribute power among the three branches of government. Post-revolution, they established a government independent from the legislature to embody the desire for a sufficiently robust central authority, thus ensuring the Constitution’s durability. Some scholars attribute the enduring nature of the US Constitution to the wisdom of its framers, who crafted a document featuring a separation and balance of powers, concise language and a judicial activism. Particularly, the judiciary’s role in interpreting the Constitution according to contemporary needs has facilitated its adaptation without formal amendments. The trust and reliance of citizens and other governmental branches on the judiciary play a pivotal role in upholding the longevity of the US Constitution. Martin H. Redish distinguishes the American Constitution as a consensual social agreement, contrasting it with the French Constitution, which is viewed as a subject of contention. As a result, the American Constitution endured, whereas the French Constitution has been subject to frequent changes.

Even in our context, the people’s expectations at the time of drafting the constitution played a pivotal role. Since the people’s movement in 2007 BS was aimed to transfer the authority from the Rana to the King, the public was not particularly focused about the constitution. Indeed, in the royal declaration made by King Tribhuvan on 7 Falgun 2007 BS he proclaimed that ‘. . . today it is our wish and decision that the government of our people should be in accordance with the republican constitution drafted by a Constituency Assembly elected by them. . .’. However, when King Mahendra came to power, he adopted the policy of dividing and ruling the political parties. Until the year 2015 BS, there was no constitution, no elections and the breakdown of democratic power, as the King manipulated the political parties. However, the political leadership at that time believed that everything could be put back on track after the enactment of a parliamentary constitution and the election of the government.

Unfortunately, the elected government did not gain momentum after the King took power. Consequently, the political parties had to struggle for the restoration of the parliamentary system for three decades.

In bourgeois democracy, there is a strong emphasis on political and civil rights and freedoms. This principle was evident in the 2046 BS people’s movement, where both local and foreign bourgeois democratic forces shared the common goal of leading the movement and ensuring it remained free from the influence of leftist ideologies. As a result, the people’s movement was characterized with limited political freedom.

After the 2046 BS people’s movement, the primary ally of the movement, the Samyukta Janamorcha, not only faced complete disregard but was also prohibited. About the constitution, which initially prioritized political and civil freedoms, along with the poor governance of elected government, the Chairman of the Maoists’ affiliate organization, Samyukta Janamorcha, Baburam Bhattarai, handed over a 40-point petition to then Prime Minister Sher Bahadur Deuba. The petition outlined various points, including the abolition of unequal treaties such as the Nepal-India Treaty of 1950 (Point No. 1); ending the dominance of monopoly capital in Nepal’s economy and establishing customs policies to foster a self-sufficient national economy (Point Nos. 6 and 7); drafting a new constitution by elected representatives to establish democracy and end royal privileges (Point Nos. 10 and 11); declaring Nepal a secular state (Point No. 18); ensuring equal rights for daughters to ancestral property (Point No. 19); ending all forms of caste-based exploitation and oppression and establishing ethnicity-based self-governance in areas where a particular ethnic community constitutes a majority (Point No. 20); eradicating discrimination against Dalits should be and completely abolishing the practice of untouchability (Point No. 21); providing equal opportunities and facilities for all language speakers, with arrangements for education in the mother tongue up to the higher secondary level (Point No. 22); strengthening and empowering local bodies (Point No. 26); and providing free and scientific health and education services for all (Point No. 35).7 The neglect of these demands by the government led to a decade-long civil war, known as the People’s War, which ultimately brought an end to the 240-year-old feudal monarchy and paved the way for a federal, republican, inclusive and secular state, leading to the drafting of a new constitution.

Although the Nepali Civil War concluded through an agreement prompted by national and international circumstances, numerous political agendas highlighted the conflict, along with certain economic, social and cultural rights, enshrined as fundamental rights in the constitution. A constitution created in the aftermath of a revolution must reflect the spirit of the movement and lay the groundwork for fulfilling its expectations. Mere words within the constitution cannot automatically meet the people’s aspirations; it is the state’s institutions and their actors that must bring them to life. The most crucial aspect is building trust among citizens that the constitution and its associated institutions are addressing their expectations. Achieving this, fosters hope among the public, although this alone does not guarantee the longevity of the constitution.

PEOPLE-ORIENTED PROVISIONS UNDER THE
NEPALI PREVAILING CONSTITUTION

Nepal underwent seven decades of both large- and small-scale armed conflicts, as well as peaceful protests and demonstrations, to achieve a comprehensive democratic constitution. Following the 2062-3 BS movement, when the Constituent Assembly enacted the new constitution in 2072 BS, it was declared that the era of political struggle had ended and the focus shifted to economic revolution. This indicated that all major political issues had been addressed through the constitution. In essence, the nation transitioned into a secular, federal and inclusive republic, where individuals from all walks of life can aspire to the highest positions in the country. The introduction of federalism has paved the way for equitable development, while the assurance of economic and social rights signifies that further political upheaval is unnecessary.

The current constitution, drafted by the Constituent Assembly, emphasizes its commitment to socialism directly in its preamble. It seeks to eradicate all forms of discrimination and oppression departing from the feudal, despotic, centralized and unitary state system, thereby ensuring social justice. Article 3 of the Constitution defines the nation with multi-ethnic, multilingual, multi-religious, multicultural characteristics, while Article 4 characterizes the state as a secular, inclusive, socialism-oriented and federal democratic republican. These foundational principles hold immense significance and pose a challenge to feudal powers.

In addition to these core provisions, the fundamental right enshrined in Part Three of the constitution—especially the newly introduced rights—highlight the socialist and inclusive character of the constitution. Article 16 affirms that every person has the right to live with dignity, implying that Nepali citizens are entitled to lead a dignified life, secured by basic rights and their effective enforcement. The responsibility of ensuring this lies with the state. Similarly, Article 24 of the Constitution guarantees the right against untouchability and discrimination as a fundamental right. This article stipulates that no person shall be subjected to any form of untouchability or discrimination in any private or public places on grounds of his or her origin, caste, tribe, community, profession, occupation or physical condition. Additionally, there should be no discrimination in the production or distribution of goods, services or facilities. It is universally recognized as a fundamental human right that individuals should not face discrimination based on factors such as gender, ethnic origin, colour, political beliefs, religious affiliations or sexual orientation.

Likewise, Article 32 provides for the right to language and culture, Article 33 guarantees the right to employment, Article 34 enshrines the right to labour, Article 35 ensures the right to health, Article 36 establishes the right to food sovereignty, Article 37 secures the right to shelter and Article 38 safeguards the rights of women. These rights represent the collective entitlements of the people. It seems that many of the demands outlined in the petition presented by the Samyukta Janamorcha prior to the enactment of the constitution have been incorporated into it.

Article 42 of the constitution outlines the right to social justice, ensuring the inclusion of socially backward classes, including women, in state bodies based on inclusive principles. Additionally, Article 42(2) mandates that indigent citizens and citizens and communities on the verge of extinction shall have the right to get special opportunities and benefits in education, health, housing, employment, food and social security for their protection, upliftment, empowerment and development.

Moreover, the guiding principles of the state in Part Four of the Constitution also reflects its socialist orientation. Due to space constraints, a detailed discussion of these principles is not feasible here.

EXAMINING CONSTITUTIONAL DURABILITY
AND STABILITY: KEY INQUIRIES

Concerns about the Constitution’s durability and stability have occasionally arisen in the seven years following its enactment. While dissatisfaction was widespread at the time of its adoption, the intensity of criticism has since diminished. Initially, certain political factions denounced the constitution as flawed, but with time, many of these groups have come to accept it in practice. In addition to participating in electoral processes under the constitution, these factions have also engaged in government formation, thereby tacitly acknowledging its provisions. What began as demands for a complete rewrite of the constitution has gradually transitioned into calls for constitutional amendments. This shift signifies a growing acceptance and adoption of the constitution. It is essential to view such demands for amendment positively, recognizing that no constitution can be immutable. To ensure its relevance and efficacy, periodic amendments and developments through formal procedures, judicial interpretations and practical applications are imperative.

In recent times, concerns regarding the stability of the constitution have emerged. These concerns do not reflect the rejection of the constitution itself but rather echoes the concern over the individuals entrusted with the responsibility of governing the state within its framework and those who have taken solemn oaths to safeguard its integrity. Notably, frequent dissolution of the House of Representatives through mechanisms not sanctioned by the constitution, reluctance to form a government despite enjoying majority support from parliamentarians and reluctance to endorse bills passed by both houses, particularly when additional questions not included in the original text of bill are raised, have reignited doubts about the constitution’s stability.

The first condition for the constitution to endure is for everyone to embrace its provisions, which entails internal acceptance. In practice, the effectiveness of the constitution is demonstrated by the exercise of rights and adherence to duties outlined within it. Distinguished jurist H.L.A. Hart suggests that for a constitution or any law to be effective, it must achieve a minimum level of effectiveness, especially in a developed society where it should be embraced and adhered to by state officials as a rule governing their formal conduct. This is also referred to as constitutional culture, which entails understanding and interpreting the constitution’s provisions. Unfortunately, we have yet to cultivate a strong constitutional culture. There is a tendency to interpret the constitution’s provisions subjectively, which poses challenges to its implementation and sustainability. This factor also contributed to the failure of the 2047 BS constitution.

It can be observed that even political factions which initially expressed extreme dissatisfaction when the constitution was promulgated, have subsequently participated in elections conducted in accordance with its provisions and have agreed to amend the constitution without revising it entirely. This suggests that discontent at the civil level is gradually dissipating. However, in such a scenario, it is gravely concerning that the responsible stakeholders of the state, who are entrusted with the guardianship of the constitution, has exceeded its constitutional limits. Given that the constitution itself grants the Supreme Court the authority to determine the constitutionality of bills and invalidate them if found to be unconstitutional, attempts made to nullify this right to interpret the constitution will be questioned for a long time.

The second vital aspect for ensuring the longevity of the constitution is fostering a sense of ownership among the populace. It is imperative for everyone to feel connected to the constitution. This sense of ownership can be nurtured through active participation in its creation and by addressing grievances through amendments. To ensure the widespread acceptance of the constitution, it is crucial to promptly address emerging issues since its promulgation. This serves as a safety mechanism for the constitution. The 2047 constitution retained certain provisions as basic principles while allowing for amendments on other matters. However, the failure to utilize this safety mechanism to address immediate grievances through amendments led to the downfall of the constitution. During discussions about amending the constitution, there were objections from the establishment side against altering trivial matters. Nonetheless, the constitution was repealed without any attempt at amendment.

The development of the constitution takes place through its application, court interpretation and through formal amendments. The things that are not in the constitution or the provisions that are not clear can be developed through good practice, which can also be referred to as organic development. To alleviate dissatisfaction with the current constitution, an acceptable amendment draft can be prepared through thorough discussion and consultation, addressing concerns through constitutional amendment. This could be a significant step toward ensuring the stability of the constitution.

In our context, the third thing necessary for the stability of the constitution is the actual projection of rights. Although the constitution has adopted a federal model, the trend of centralization of rights has not improved. It is necessary for everyone to understand that all three levels of government are under the rule of the constitution and are independent in their areas and should function accordingly. Our political leadership has not internalized the function of provincial government and local bodies as that of government.

The fourth condition for the longevity constitution is the democratization of institutions. Democracy demands participation, discussion and transparency in policymaking. The more the state institutions are democratic, the people’s trust in democracy increases. This helps in the longevity of the democratic constitution.

The fifth important condition is good governance and development. People want to improve their standard of living. Moreover, democracy is for advanced and prosperous life. The constitution is not an end but a means to achieve a high and prosperous life through the democratic process. No matter how good the constitution is, if prosperity is not achieved, the people will not be satisfied. Therefore, we should be able to make the people optimistic that this constitution is ours, the government is for us and the government works for our welfare.

The sixth condition is the actual participation of the people. The current elections are only formal and syndicate based. Elections are expensive. There have been instances where some good politicians have hesitated to contest the election. It is necessary to improve the electoral system and make it less expensive. As a result, people’s participation will increase, people’s democracy will be established and the people themselves will protect and own the democratic constitution.

The seventh condition is the democratization of political parties. Political parties are the cornerstone of democracy. Apparently, there is lack of internal democracy in political parties. The political parties operate with a bureaucratic approach that is subject to the whims of certain leaders. To increase people’s faith in democracy, parties themselves should adopt democratic practices. Enhanced internal democratic practices strengthen democracy, foster the growth of democratic culture and consequently heighten public appeal.

The eighth thing is to develop a sense of responsibility. Democracy is a system of public accountability. If the people feel that the representatives sent by them are sensitive and responsible towards them, they will believe in political parties, democracy and the constitution.

The ninth thing is to implement the inclusiveness adopted by the constitution in practice. At present, inclusivity is not given attention in state agencies, political parties or election candidates. The people’s faith in the constitution cannot be maintained when the expectations that led to participation in the democratic movement are not fulfilled.

The tenth and last condition is the practical implementation of various economic, social and cultural rights guaranteed by the constitution. The practical implementation of important economic, social and cultural rights such as the right to live in a clean environment, the right to education, the right to language and religion, the right to food, the right to housing, the right to social security, the right to health and the right to consumers is essential for the perpetuation of the constitution.

However, the situation is different in the twentieth century. Constitutions enacted after the revolutions largely resembles the revolutionary manifestos, often structured upon the ideals and accomplishments of original social revolutions, aiming to comprehensively reshape established civil societies. These therefore aim at completely dismantling previous structures and redefining them with a view of integrating previously excluded groups into the country’s governance. Even though they are considered as instruments of change, sometimes they show a society-state connection that is far from reality hence calling for reforms whenever there is a wide difference between fiction and truth. As such, amendments or changes have been sought to build a new political order through constitutionality. However, if the power structure of the state cannot be fully reshaped then it becomes difficult to implement such constitutions practically. The effective implementation of constitutional provisions necessitates cooperation from all institutions within the state structure, including the courts, military, police and other constitutional and administrative bodies. Without such cooperation, the realization of constitutional provisions becomes unattainable. Currently, we are experiencing a similar situation.

CONCLUSION

In conclusion, the constitution stands as the cornerstone of the political landscape, which is rightly recognized as a political-legal document. Our prevailing constitution reflects a compromise between established and emerging powers, akin to a contractual agreement where rights and responsibilities are distributed among all stakeholders. Upholding the longevity of our democratic constitution requires firm commitment from all the stakeholders to adhere to its principles. This emphasizes the importance of fostering a democratic culture among political actors, guiding their actions to align with constitutional provisions. Furthermore, embracing judicial interpretations is crucial for ensuring the resilience of our democratic system in the long run.

NOTES

1. Freeman, M.D.A. (2021). Lloyd’s Introduction to Jurisprudence. London, Sweet and Maxwell, Reprinted in India, p. 958.

2. Ibid.

3. Daniel J. Elazar (1990). Constitution-Making: The Pre-eminently Political Act, Constitutionalism: The Israeli and American Experiences, JCPA, https://www.jcpa.org/dje/articles3/constisramer.htm.

4. Tom Ginsburg et al. (2009). ‘The Endurance of National Constitutions’, Cambridge University Press, p. 1.

5. Ibid.

6. Steven Mintz, ‘Historical Context: The Survival of the US Constitution’, https://www.gilderlehrman.org/history-resources/teaching-resource/historical-context-survival-us-constitution

7. Baburam’s demand to Baburam himself, Retrieved from https://mysansar.com/2012/06/506/

REFERENCES

Bhattarai, Baburam (2012). Baburam’s demand to Baburam himself. Retrieved from https://mysansar.com/2012/06/506/

Elazar, D.J. (1990). Constitution-making: The Pre-eEinentlyPolitical Act. In Constitutionalism: The Israeli and American Experiences. Retrieved from https://www.jcpa.org/dje/articles3/constisramer.htm

Freeman, M.D.A. (2021). Lloyd’s Introduction to Jurisprudence. London: Sweet and Maxwell.

Ginsburg, T., Elkins, Z., and Melton, J. (2009). The Endurance of National Constitutions. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.

Mintz, S. (n.d.). Historical Context: The Survival of the US Constitution. Retrieved from https://www.gilderlehrman.org/history-resources/teaching-resource/historical-context-survival-us-constitution.

CHAPTER 9

Nepal-United States Relations in the
Context of Increased Chinese
Influence in South Asia

PURNA BAHADUR KARKI

INTRODUCTION

Nepal and the United States established diplomatic relations in 1948. The US has been helping to support Nepal in promoting political stability and economic development and providing humanitarian assistance. Furthermore, the US assists Nepal through bilateral relations for peace and security. Globally, the US and Nepal support each other to achieve both nations’ policies and objectives in the international community. Nepal is becoming one of the most important countries to US policy to obtain South Asian security and monitor Chinese and Indian militarism and nuclear security, as well as Pakistani extremism. In contemporary discourse, the presence of the US in South Asia also impacts the global influence of the US.

Historically and in the literature, the Second World War, the Cold War, the post-Cold War era, the aftermath of 9/11, and China’s emergence since 2004-5 have all highlighted the importance of South Asia and the Indian Ocean in maintaining and sustaining the superpower image and influence of the US in Asia. When examined, the US policy pursued in South Asia and West Asia during Second World War and the Cold War shows that Sri Lanka supported US interests in countering Russian presence in the region. This indicates how important South Asia is in the US policy and stability programmes, not regional considerations but also for controlling communism and reinforcing but also for controlling communism and reinforcing the US superpower in contemporary Asia.

Additionally, when US policy toward South Asia indirectly was evaluated and observed, through Japan and India, as proxies of the US that implement US policy. Japan has represented the US ever since 9/11 to revitalize and activate policy against global terrorism. The US has sought loyal partners in South Asia and India is a reliable partner just like Japan.

China will collide with the US. It is emerging as an economic powerhouse and is spontaneously threatening US interests, influence and even position in South Asia. China is challenging the superpower image and influence of the US. This first took place in South Asia, where traditional allies of the US, such as Pakistan, Sri Lanka and the Maldives are looking to China for economic and development assistance.

In addition to its political, economic and security interests, China is in search of new markets for investment. China is focusing on giving assistance, such as long-term loans and expertise to South Asian nations, such as Pakistan, Sri Lanka and Nepal and has actively engaged in the region. China proposed the Asian Infrastructure Investment Bank, which will enhance the position of China if it becomes active. This will reduce the influence of the US and Japan. Given these conditions, the US must review its policy program to challenge the Chinese presence.

In its development perspective and policy ‘One Belt and One Road’ (OBOR), China proposes establishing and creating a network of railways, roads, pipelines and utility grid that would link China and other central Asian nations, which would pave the way for connecting China and the world. This would boost the Chinese involvement in this region, as well as providing a platform for economic cooperation, including policy coordination, trade and financing collaboration and social and cultural cooperation. This would enhance the Chinese initiative towards a leadership position in the world forum, where recently US policy and programmes have worked against the member countries. Also, Trump’s policy of ‘America First’ opens the US to more criticism in international relations, which might be problematic for sustaining a US leadership role in the world forum.

Further, in the future, how China builds its military power against traditional American allies will determine the superpower image of the US in the region. Moreover, recent developments involving regional tension and allies, as well as national internal conflicts, have gone against American interests. In this situation, the American policy programme is important in Asia, where China, North Korea, South Korea, Philippines and Japan are all suffering from internal conflicts involving security and disputes in the South China Sea.

Recently, the media, politicians and academics have debated the leadership change in the US government in the Trump era in both positive and negative ways. Trump’s bilateralism may provide more opportunities for the American people and may build stronger bonds with the international community. However, some fear that extreme policies might reduce US global power. But not only it gives the US a clear road to power but also provides security for the US. In this chapter, the following hypotheses are tested:

(i) Trump’s bilateralism policy will have good/ bad implications for stability in Asia.

(ii) Nepal can play an important role as an intermediary between the US and China.

Further, explorations regarding relations between the US and Nepal in the context of China’s increased influence in South Asia during the Trump era is done.

METHODOLOGY

This research employed a multifaceted approach to data collection and analysis, with a strong emphasis on qualitative methods. Secondary data were gathered through an extensive literature review and systematic comparison. To gain a comprehensive understanding of contemporary discourse concerning Nepal and the United States, as well as their politico-economic and societal contexts, qualitative aspects of social components were meticulously examined. Additionally, historical analysis was conducted to contextualize these findings within a broader temporal framework.

NEPAL AND INDIA RELATIONS IN THE CONTEXT
OF INCREASED CHINESE INFLUENCE
IN SOUTH ASIA

Nepal and India have cordial bilateral relations and they share common cultural elements, traditions, and religion. According to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs on Nepal-India relations, it states that the two countries established diplomatic relations on 17 June 1947. In principles of peaceful coexistence, sovereign equality and understanding of each other’s aspiration and sensitivities, Nepal and India not only have relations through treaties and agreements between the two countries but also have people-to-people contact and free movements of people between the countries. At the political level, Nepal and India have good relations, with frequent high-level visits by the leaders between the two countries. Recently, for example, Prime Ministers exchanged visits within a short period. This illustrates the importance of India-Nepal relations at the political level.

Looking back to Nepalese leaders’ state visits to India, it indicates that almost all Nepali political leaders and Prime Minsters visited India after they assumed office. Reciprocally, an invitation from Nepal’s then Prime Minister, Sushil Koirala, led to an official visit to Nepal in August 2014, by the Prime Minister of India, His Excellency Shri Narendra Modi. This was a historic visit by a prime minister of India to Nepal, after 17 years, which reflected the commitment of the newly-formed government in India to enhance India’s relations with neighbouring countries (Ministry of Foreign Affair, Nepal, 2017. This indicates the importance of Nepal relations to India after the change of leadership in India in response to China’s increasing development assistance and engagement in this region.

In relation to the Prime Minster of India’s third visit on Nepal within a four-years’ period, Thapa (2018) states, ‘India has realized by now that the use of coercive diplomacy severely dented bilateral relations. Therefore, India wants to revamp its image in Nepal and Modi’s reciprocal visit within a month of Oli’s visit to India signals the urge and necessity to do so’. Also, Bagachi Indrani (2018) states that it is ‘to reset ties’. Analysis of the state level visits and Indian engagements indicates that its diplomatic course and policy are shifting towards Nepal. A review of ongoing engagements of Nepal’s friends to Nepal’s development and their assistance and aid reflect that China-Nepal-India trilateral relations are becoming more viable than before.

Further, when the political parties and their ideology are considered, Nepal’s and India’s governments have different political ideology but Nepal and China have communist governments. A basic assumption is that Nepal faces challenges in maintaining balanced relations with both neighbours. The perception is that, due to its communist government, some scholars and others predict that Nepal will incline more toward China, which India would perceive as a security threat to Indian security interests. However, it is arguable that, whether governments have the same ideology or not, China always supports those who are in government, as well as their decisions, rather than following communist ideology. On the other hand, India’s diplomacy is now slightly changed and has a political tone. Moreover, the cultural factors and open borders are strong influences, so that in the future Nepal, India and China relations will be stronger than in the past. However, one cannot ignore that China and India both have an interest in Nepal and that both nations want to make their presence felt in Nepal.

For Nepal, India has been the key development partner. India had been supporting Nepal in developing projects and political affairs during the insurgency and time of mass movements. India has been assisting Nepal in different sectors through economic assistance to Nepal, such as infrastructure development, capacity development of human resources and initiation of large and intermediate project that have been undertaken with Indian economic assistance. Nepal does not have direct contact to seaports, so its trade depends mostly on the Indian market. India and Nepal have a bilateral treaty on transit, a treaty on trade and agreements of cooperation to control unauthorized trade. The foregoing provides both national investment and trade facilities and provide Nepal with transit facilities to support third country trade.

For China and Nepal, due to geographical structure and complication, there are not many options or routes for trade and transit points between Nepal and China. Only the Rasuwagadhi-Kerung border trade and transit point has been updated to international standards after the great earthquake which damaged the transit point and closed border link roads.

Since the earthquake and the blockade along the Nepal-India border in September 2015, Nepal has become closer to China as it has tried to find alternatives to trade and transit to India, allowing China to step into the Nepali market that was, in past, India’s monopoly. Further, according to the diplomat newspaper through the ‘One Belt, One Road’ initiative, Beijing is looking into the possibility of connecting Kathmandu to Lhasa in Tibet via railways at an estimated cost of $8 billion. China’s activities have been steadily expanding in Nepal after Kathmandu’s support for OBOR materialized. This happened despite India’s stiff resistance to ‘OBOR’. So, for both neighbours, Nepal is an important friend for not only their economic interests but also in multilateral and regional fora.

China’s engagement in South Asia and Nepal contributes to more assertive diplomacy and friendship between Nepal and India. Meanwhile, both neighbours and Nepal’s political parties are reluctant to act based on their ideology but Nepal’s government aims for a balanced foreign policy towards its neighbours. According to the Constitution of Nepal, foreign policy of Nepal is guided by abiding faith in the United Nations and the policy of non-alignment. It includes:

• Mutual respect for each other’s territorial integrity and sovereignty.

• Non-interference in each other’s internal affairs.

• Respect for mutual equality.

• Non-aggression and the peaceful settlement of disputes.

• Cooperation for mutual benefit.

Contact between the people of China and Nepal is restricted. Both countries require visa, unlike with India and Nepal. However, the relations of Nepal and India are cordial, with bilateral agreements. Considering the social and cultural bonds that both countries have in common, it can be said that they are like family. Both countries have people-to-people relations that are stronger than state level, such that the countries are culturally and socially connected.

CHINESE ACTIVISM IN SOUTH ASIA AND
TRADITIONAL US INFLUENCE

In the twenty-first century, South Asia has experienced many changes caused by internal and external factors that affected the political stability of South Asian region. Since the 9/11 terrorist attacks, world politics and country polarization have occurred globally, impacting South Asia. This divided nations into two sides concerning the global war against terrorism. US had influence around the world, making India and US a strategic partnership against terrorism and in global issues, which further made India an emerging US ally in South Asian region. In the international forum and among South Asian national issues, the US has tried to view Nepal and other South Asian countries through the Indian perspective, depending on Indian analysis. This strengthened Indian and US influence on South Asian issues in politics, human rights and international cooperation.

Recently, however, the change in leadership in the US and India has had direct effects on the politics and regional alliances and structures. For the structure of power balance in contemporary Asia, India, China, the US and Japan all play vital roles for stability and peace in this region. Leadership that is transformational, reformative and constructive is needed, however, US President Trump’s bilateralism policy has already distanced the US. from global and multilateral alliances, which can jeopardy the US global superpower image. This already shows effects on trade, immigration and political fora. In international relations, the US is losing its hegemony. This distancing from the global alliances, resulting from the rejection of the Trans-Pacific Partnership (TPP), the pull-out from the Paris Climate Accords, Jagannathan (2017) places the US at odds with the G7 on an agreement which 195 nations have signed and 147 have formally ratified. This set back the US global superpower image and hegemony in international relations. In the case of South Asian countries, the US had previously expressed their political interest through their alliances, such as with Japan and India, in terms of economics assistance and support and cooperation in global fora.

In contrast to the actions of the US, China is expanding its presence in South Asia and in international relations. In South Asia, China is developing good relations with countries, such as Sri Lanka, Pakistan and Maldives and offering economic assistance without any conditions. As a result, countries that traditionally relied on Indian and US assistance are now accepting Chinese support. Thus, China’s trade and growing engagement on this region is bringing other South Asian states under China’s influence. China’s engagement in Pakistan, for example, with investment in infrastructure projects and collaborations on security and defence, indicate its growing presence in this region.

In the context of possible policy options for Nepal in response to both growing Chinese and US influence and the future consequences of Trump’s policy of bilateralism, Nepal can gain advantages from both India and China. Under Trump’s policies, Nepal might not continue to get assistance that the US had previously given and as a result suffers. Although Nepal can propose, on its own, conditions in international fora to support US policy which benefit Nepal. However, the current situation is that the US and India are trying to influence Nepal’s close relationship and policies towards China, considering these as threats for their superpower image in areas such as refugee issues and human rights issues.

In the context of India and China, there is a significant possibility that both nations will be inclined to support the development of Nepali projects. This inclination is driven by their competitive efforts to establish Nepal as a strategic ally.

CONCLUSION

After the World War Two, the US highlighted its national interest and that became a globalized priority through an emerging new world order. This US policy focused on developing an international order based on economic interdependence and multilateralism and strategic alliances under US leadership. This promoted US leadership and hegemony. Recent changes in leadership and bilateralism show the US distancing itself from global fora. This may cause instability, risk the security of its allies and have a negative impact on globalization. Although, for some, this gives a positive interpretation to the ‘America First’ slogan, it positions nationalism first, whereas, in this century, almost all elements are interconnected and globalized, requiring multilateralism.

In the larger Asia, South Asia is important, with China, India and Pakistan all nuclear countries. China’s activism in South Asia gives it an opportunity to lead the world in terms of trade with India and South Asian states, which gives control of a large market. China’s trade with the US and the African continent and its participation in international fora, give China increased influence, particularly considering the US pulling out of international collaborations and commitments.

India and China can contribute in a major way to the stability and development of the South Asian region. In the long term, US traditional relations and influence on security, as well as the US Indian strategic partnership, are still viable, due to Pakistani and Chinese factors. The US India strategic relationship plays a critical role to check the balance between India, China and Pakistan.

Nepal-India relations, relative to increased Chinese influence, provide the possibility of more options for Nepal and India in economic cooperation, with both countries benefiting.

REFERENCES

Chollet, Derek and James Goldgeier, 2008, ‘America between the Wars, from 11/9 to 9/11: The Misunderstood Years between the Fall of the Berlin Wall and the Start of the War on Terror’. New York: Public Affairs.

Cronin, Richard, 2005,‘The North Korea Nuclear Threat and the U.S. Japan Security Alliance: Perceived Interests, Approaches, and Prospects’, The Fletcher Forum of World Affairs, vol. 29, no. 1, p. 51-73.

Jagannathan, Meera, 2017, ‘Here are all the terrible things President Trump has said about NAFTA—before deciding to stick with it’, New York Daily News, 27 April 2017, http://www.nydailynews.com/news/politics/terriblepresident-trump-nafta-article-1.3107104 (accessed on 16 June 2018).

Kausikan, Bilahari, 2017, ‘Asia in the Trump Era, in Council on Foreign Relations.’ https://www.foreignaffairs.com/reviews/review-essay/2017-04-17/asia-trump-era (accessed on 18 March 2018).

Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Nepal, 2018, Nepal India-relation, https://mofa.gov.np/nepal-india-relations/ (accessed on 20 July 2018).

Pant, Harsh V., 2017, ‘China’s Moment in Nepal: Implications for India’ in The Diplomat, 27 December 2017. https://thediplomat.com/2017/12/chinas-moment-in-nepal-implications-for-india/ (accessed on 23 July 2018).

Santoro, D. and J. Warden, 2015, ‘Assuring Japan and South Korea in the Second Nuclear Age’, The Washington Quarterly, 38: 1. <https://twq.elliott.gwu.edu/sites/twq.elliott.gwu.edu/files/downloads/TWQ_Spring2015_Santoro-Warden.pdf> (accessed on 16 June 2018).

Singh, Santosh, 2016, US Policy and Approach Towards Bangladesh, Nepal and Sri Lanka 1992-2003, Morrisville: Lulu Publication.

Sutter, Robert G. 2015, ‘The United States and Asia: Regional Dynamics and Twenty-First Century Relations’, MD, Rowman & Littlefield.

Thapa, Gaurab S., 2018, ‘New Outlook in Nepal’s Relations with India and China.’ In Asia Times on 7 May 2018. http://www.atimes.com/new-outlook-in-nepals-relations-with-india-and-china/ (accessed on 25 June 2018).

The Asia Foundation, 2016, ‘Asian Views on America’s Role in Asia: The Future of the Rebalance: Strategic Recommendations for the Incoming U.S. President on Foreign Policy towards Asia’, The vAsia Foundation.